<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The king's request: or, Dauid's desire A sermon preached at the last generall fast holden at Yorke, the 21. of Aprill last. By Phinees Hodson Doctour of Diuinity, and Chancellour of the Metropoliticall Church of St. Peter-Yorke.</title>
            <author>Hodson, Phineas, d. 1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 58 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03425</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13551</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104137</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839876</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839876</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4335</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03425)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4335)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1208:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The king's request: or, Dauid's desire A sermon preached at the last generall fast holden at Yorke, the 21. of Aprill last. By Phinees Hodson Doctour of Diuinity, and Chancellour of the Metropoliticall Church of St. Peter-Yorke.</title>
                  <author>Hodson, Phineas, d. 1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 34 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Harper, for Edward Blount, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4335:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4335:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE KING'S REQVEST: OR, DAVID'S DESIRE.</p>
            <p>A Sermon preached at the laſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall <hi>Faſt</hi> holden at <hi>Yorke,</hi> the 21. of <hi>Aprill</hi> laſt.</p>
            <p>By PHINEES HODSON Doctour of Diuinity, and Chancellour of the Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticall Church of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Peter-Yorke.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's or publisher's device</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by THO. HARPER, for <hi>Edward Blount,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1628.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:4335:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:4335:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>PSAL. 27.4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>One thing haue J deſired of the Lord, which I will require, euen that I may dwell in the houſe of the Lord all the dayes of my life, to behold the beauty of the Lord, and to viſit his Temple.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this Pſalme you haue the Prophet keeping an Audit, and taking a reckoning of the treaſures of his heart: the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts were many and great,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 12.35.</note> which like ſo many Riuers from that great Ocean of Gods mercy, made glad his heart, that was a man after Gods heart, 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 13.14.</p>
            <p>For the receipts you ſhall finde them acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in all his accounts. To ſeeke no further; an infinite treaſure, greater then <hi>Solomons,</hi> is mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the firſt verſe of this Pſalme, the Lord is his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:4335:3"/> light, his ſtrength, his ſaluation. My text disbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that treaſure in thankfull deuotion. <hi>One thing &amp;c.</hi> And we haue reaſon to take our riſe hence, to begin at thankes: for we haue receiued much. And to receiue much, and reſtore nothing, is a ſhame. It's a ſhame not to giue, where there's cauſe; a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſhame not to reſtore; and ſhame ſeldome goes alone, but is accompanied either with ſorrow, or paine, or both, at leaſt attended, There being no burthen that loades more then a benefit; and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens if they bee heauy, are both ſorrowfull and painfull.</p>
            <p>Indeed aske a naturall man, what is the greateſt burthen, and he will tell you ſorrow. Aske a ſpirituall man, and he will ſay Sinne. Sorrow loades man; But Sinne loades man and God himſelfe, yea and tyers him too. Thou haſt made me to ſerue with thy ſinnes, (a meane office to put God to) and wearied me with thy tranſgreſſions, <hi>Iſ.</hi> 43.24.</p>
            <p>But aske the morall man, what is the greateſt bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, and he will tell you a benefit. The Prophet <hi>David</hi> had experience of all theſe. He complaines of his ſonne, and great was his ſorrow, that he that came out of his owne bowels ſought his life. But he roares for his ſinne.</p>
            <p>And when theſe tempeſts were ouerblowne, he was not quiet in the calme, but was after a ſerious medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion put to his, <hi>Quid retribuam, What ſhall I giue vnto the Lord for all the benefits that hee hath done vnto me.</hi> And this in effect is his labour now, there he conſulted, <hi>Quid retribuam;</hi> here hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolued: <hi>One thing haue I deſired, &amp;c.</hi> For in the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:4335:3"/> three firſt verſes before my Text, hee made a diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery of Gods mercy and bounty. In my Text hee vowes his ſeruice, as the tribute of his dutie. For though it be <hi>Vnum petij,</hi> he went not onely to pray, but to offer ſacrifices of ioy, and to ſing and praiſe the Lord, verſe 6.</p>
            <p>For thankfulneſſe is <hi>Debitum morale;</hi> and the Ciuilians ſay <hi>Naturaliter obligamur à dante.</hi> So that, as it is a heauy thing to beare, either in body or conſcience, ſo are not they releaſed that are relea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. The very act of deliuery drawing on a third burthen how to be thankfull, which vnleſſe we take vp, a worſe than either of the other will happen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs. Therefore in the nine leapers that returned not to giue thanks, to take vp this burthen, <hi>Luc.</hi> 17. <hi>Vlcus ingratitudinis,</hi> was (ſaid one) more loathſome then they leproſie the had? for they were <hi>Mundi cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te,</hi> but not <hi>Corde.</hi> Chriſt had giuen them faire skins, but they had made themſelues foule hearts.</p>
            <p>But a good man is euer thankfull. If <hi>Eliſha</hi> haue houſe-roome with the Shunamite, before hee take his leaue, <hi>What ſhall we do for thee</hi> 2 K. 4.13. And if <hi>Ionathan</hi> be dead, <hi>David</hi> will enquire for ſome of <hi>Sauls</hi> kindred to gratifie them for his friend <hi>Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans</hi> ſake, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 9.3. yea vnthankfull <hi>Abſalom</hi> will condemne ingrate <hi>Huſhai,</hi> though himſelfe gaine by it, is this thy kindneſſe to thy friend? 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.17. yea the Deuill himſelfe damnes it, <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.9. and cons him not thank that leanes to one that ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports him. Doth <hi>Iob</hi> ſerue God for nothing? And as the thing is odious, for, <hi>In hac contumelia omnis contumelia;</hi> ſo is the name: he is a <hi>Nabal,</hi> a foole,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:4335:4"/> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 25.25. a title in theſe times more contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble than a knaue, when the world is more aſhamed of infirmities, then crimes, and it is greater reproach to be eſteemed ſhallow then wicked. And as both the thing, and the name is odious, ſo it is vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable. For as it's true; He that ſmoothers one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iury, drawes on a ſecond; So he that vnthankfully ſmoothers a benefit, loſeth a ſecond. And againe, as he that quits one wrong, preuents many; So he that quits a benefit, inuites many. For, <hi>Nunquam ceſſabit decurſus gratiarum à Deo, niſi prius ceſſet recurſus gratiarum ab homine, The ſhowres of Gods graces will neuer leaue falling vpon vs, ſo long as wee ſend back but the fruit of thankfullneſſe to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then before we aske new bleſſings, let vs bee thankfull for the old;<note place="margin">Eighty eight and powder treaſon.</note> we haue within many of our memories, beene deliuered both from deſtruction by water, and fire. Some of vs, euen of late, from famine, and many of vs from the peſtilence. Wee of this Citie ſo preſerued from it, as it hath not beene ſuffered in that common calamity, to come neare our dwellings. And now Lord make vs thankfull, and in mercy, not in wrath, preſerue vs from the ſword. It were a ſecret, worth our diſcoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, what's the motiue to Gods patience towards vs, that all our neighbour countryes ſhould bee in blood, and worſe, and the ſword of the deuourer ſhould not be able to touch vs. I ſay in blood, and worſe. For God hath a plague, both on this ſide, and beyond death, worſe than death. On this ſide captiuitie, and idolatry. Beyond it; That fearfull and eternall ſeparation of our bodies and ſoule from
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:4335:4"/> God. From both which good Lord deliuer vs.</p>
            <p>And that he may deliuer vs, let vs pray that hee would ſend ſuch a gratious raine vpon his inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance as may refreſh it, and open it ſo in thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe towards him as it may expect the later raine, and not be deceiued. Theſe ſhowres they were that made the Prophet <hi>Davids</hi> heart ſo fruitfull. In the three firſt verſes of this Pſalme they fall vpon him. In my Text the fruit of thoſe ſhowres returne to God.</p>
            <p>In the firſt God is gratious vnto <hi>David.</hi> In my Text <hi>David</hi> is thankfull vnto God.</p>
            <p>The parts are three and thoſe three are in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner one. For God, <hi>David,</hi> and the Temple, make vp euery part. And theſe three make vp the three parts.</p>
            <p>For firſt you haue <hi>David</hi> praying for one thing.</p>
            <p>There's God, <hi>David</hi> and the Temple. For that one thing in the ſecond place is the Temple of the Lord, where he deſires of God hee may euer dwell. There againe is God, <hi>David,</hi> and the Temple. And thirdly, the end of his deſire to dweell there: to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the beauty of the Lord, and to viſite his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. There againe is God, <hi>Dauid,</hi> and the Temple.</p>
            <p>So the parts are three, and theſe are one, and one hath all. But in euery of theſe, one is moſt eminent; in the firſt <hi>David,</hi> in the ſecond the Temple, in the third God.</p>
            <p>Friſt <hi>David</hi> in his humble maieſtie; A petitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and therein humble. But importunate, and therein he weares a badge of maieſtie.</p>
            <p>In the ſecond the Temple (indeed the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:4335:5"/> in her glory, the Lords houſe; for a houſe can haue no greater honour then to be <hi>domus Dei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the third you haue God diſcouer'd in his ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt forme. The beauty of the Lord, which made <hi>Davids</hi> heart and his tongue run vpon that place where he beheld ſuch beauty.</p>
            <p>Of theſe the firſt is for the ſecond, and both are for the laſt. He prayes in the firſt part, and the end of his prayer in the ſecond place, is, that hee may dwell in Gods houſe. And he prayes to dwell there in the third place, that he may behold his beauty.</p>
            <p>In the firſt he is a ſuitor to God. His ſuit makes way that he may be ſoiourner with God. He ſues to ſoiourne and that not for a time, but all the dayes of his life, that hee may ſee his beauty. For that was the Architectonicon to all his deſires and endeuours.</p>
            <p>Hee prayes to God, and will haue no nay; for that he deſires, he will require. Secondly if he may be heard, he would dwell in a place, from whence he would neuer remooue, all the dayes of his life. And no maruell if importunate in his ſuit, no maruell if pleaſed with his ſeat, that had ſuch a proſpect, ſuch a ſpectacle, as the beauty of the Lord.</p>
            <p>This appeares. He that ſets vp his reſt on Gods ſeruice, ſhall finde and ſee that ſhall euer delight him. But hee muſt be deſirous and diligent too, whom God admits to behold his beauty. He that ſo loues God, as he makes him his <hi>Vnum,</hi> his dar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, will be diligent: for nothing works diligence ſo much as loue: hence is <hi>Ditectio</hi> one of loues names. And he that is diligent ſhall ſuerly ſpeed.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:4335:5"/> Let but <hi>Mary</hi> be ſo diligent as to riſe early, and come firſt to the Sepulchre and ſhe ſhall firſt ſee Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, <hi>Mark.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>And this <hi>Vt Videam</hi> is the Center of my Text, wherein all the lines of the circumſtances meet, his <hi>Petij,</hi> his <hi>Requiram.</hi> For this he prayed, for this he importuned. This was his <hi>Vnum</hi> that ſo ſeriouſly ſent him to God, for this he would bee in Gods houſe, not onely repaire thither, but dwell there, and that not for a time, but all the dayes of his life, all was to this end <hi>Vt Videam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to the parts wherein <hi>David</hi> the King ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares with his <hi>Petij.</hi> To deſire and pray is ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary with Gods Saints, but to tell of it is not ſo. Here he tels what he had done, and what hee will do. He had prayed; this is worth the enquiry, why he tels vs what he had done. He had no doubt found extraordinary comfort by it, and could not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale it.</p>
            <p>For when perſecuted by <hi>Saul,</hi> he had many ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and few friends; ſuffered much, and in reaſon could ſee no end of his ſorrow; by his prayers he ſeeks to ſupport and ſuſtaine himſelfe, in that his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate condition. Nor was he fruſtrated of his hope, God ſpeakes peace vnto him; and thence he cheeres himſelfe in his God, from whom he receiued aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, that in his owne time, he would make good that honour which he begun in him.</p>
            <p>Hence in the midſt of all dangers, he not onely eſcapes, not onely feares not, but with confidence triumphs ouer his enemies. The Lord is my light, and my ſaluation, whom then ſhall I feare: their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:4335:6"/> rage and fury was ſo farre from ouerthrowing him that they were not able to ſhake him. A houſe may ſhake and yet ſtand many a day. But all their forces cannot make him affraid. And to manifeſt his cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, he doubles his chalenge, <hi>Quem timebo, à quo trepidabo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet it ſeemes there was cauſe why he ſhould feare. For his enemies came with that confidence againſt him, that they came rather to the ſlaughter than to battell, to deuoure than to fight; for they <hi>came to eat vp his fleſh,</hi> the ſecond verſe of this Pſalme: ſo great was the ods. But the ods was not ſo great for them at firſt, as it was againſt them at laſt: for <hi>they ſtumbled and fell</hi> verſe 2. But <hi>hee was ſet vpon a rock</hi> verſe 5. and <hi>his head was lifted vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue his enemies round about him,</hi> verſe 6. They lower for all their power, and aduantage: he high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er that ſeemed a prey vnto their teeth.</p>
            <p>But though he haue eſcaped hitherto, it will not be ſo ſtill. The pitcher goes often to the Well, but at laſt comes broken home; what if <hi>Sauls</hi> troopes were diſapointed, or defeated; it cannot ſerue his turne. An army is prepared, nay ready in the field; all waies are laid to intercept him, and if they miſſe, and he ſtand out for a time, the warre ſhall bee continued, which ſhall neuer end, but with his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            <p>For all this <hi>David</hi> is ſtill where he was. Nor army can daunt him, nor further preparation driue him from his truſt, the verſe before my Text.</p>
            <p>But how came he to this courage? whence got he this aſſurance? ſurely euen in the Sanctuary
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:4335:6"/> where malefactors themſelues are freed. And ſhall not God ſecure his children that ſerue him there, that's content wicked men be ſafe that fly thither?</p>
            <p>He had learned and found in the Sanctuary, that the Lord was his light, and his ſaluation; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of ſuch comfort he could neuer haue enough, whilſt his enemies are in the field, he betakes him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the Church; this was his care, this his en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deauour, this his ſute, <hi>Vnum petij.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others aſſail'd, fly to worldly ſuccours, they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide armies, and mony, the ſinewes of armies, and all great actions. They enter treaties, conclude leagues, ſtrengthen themſelues by factions and friends, build Magizins for munition, raiſe Forts, fortifie Citadels and Caſtels, take all courſes to ſtrengthen themſelues, and weaken their aduerſaries.</p>
            <p>What <hi>David</hi> in this caſe did this way, I examine not; perhaps he had ſometimes more, ſometimes leſſe of theſe aduantages. But whatſoeuer elſe hee did, he ſlipt not this, to get himſelfe either in his perſon or his deſire to Gods houſe. Other things to him were but the By, this was the Maine of his ſtrength: you would thinkt it were all, By and Maine, for it was his <hi>Vnum.</hi> And if it were not all he did, it was all he deſired to doe. If he wanted any thing, there he ſped. If he got any thing there by his thankfulneſſe, he had it doubled. Therefore would he dwell there to pray too, and praiſe God all the dayes of his life.</p>
            <p>Surely our condition in many reſpects is not vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>Davids,</hi> for if wee looke vpon the number and ſtrength of our aduerſaries, they are many more then
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:4335:7"/> his were, &amp; reaſon we haue to beleeue, that whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they attempt an inuaſion, they will in confidence of their forces come to eat vs vp rather than to fight. The Pope, the Emperor, the King of <hi>Spaine, France</hi> now. And vaſt <hi>Germany,</hi> that had wont to bee a Bulwark againſt the Turke, and an out-worke for vs againſt the approach of the Spaniard. Now in a manner rac't or raiſ'd againſt vs. And all theſe are but the heads of many confederacies able to furniſh out great and terrible forces: yea I would to God we had not cauſe to feare (beſides that of our ſinnes) a worme and a moath at home, as dangerous as all theſe.</p>
            <p>Againſt all which, had we but <hi>Davids</hi> affection and reſolution; then ſhould we bee confident, that in the time of trouble he would hide vs, in his Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle; for if we dwell there, he will ſurely keepe vs ſafe.</p>
            <p>Indeed States-men and Gouernours, ſhould not ſo farre tempt God, as to neglect ordinary ſuccours. And his gracious maieſty hath by his Proclamation ſignified his care that way. But how few doth that charge import. Then whilſt they prouide armes, let vs goe to our prayers, whilſt they conſult, what's fit, let vs caſt our ſelues downe before his foot-ſtoole, and craue a bleſſing on their labours, that he would giue them the ſpirit of wiſdome to direct, and the ſpirit of courage to execute that which ſhall tend to the glory of God, and the good of this Church and commonwealth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>So ſhall you, euen all you, though decrepit old men, though weake women, be as the horſmen and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ots
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:4335:7"/> of fire round about</hi> Eliſha, 2 K. 6. and thereby ſhall more be with vs then againſt vs.</p>
            <p>For compute I pray you, the Citie ſo ancient,<note place="margin">Yorke.</note> ſo numerous in Pariſhes and people, at theſe times of Parliament, ſends but two to conſult (and I wiſh you had ſo conſulted of thoſe two as might haue preuented that charge and combuſtion, and fracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which ſince hath followed) theſe two repreſent the deſires of the whole Citie, and by their act you are all bound. So are there for this great and famous ſhire but two Knights, and for the ſeuerall Bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough townes two Burgeſſes.</p>
            <p>Take them together, and often, perhaps twenty thouſand appeares for the reſt.</p>
            <p>If it ſhould come to blowes, and God knowes how ſoone that may be, the ods will be leſſe, though great ſtill. Of all the men in this Kingdome, not one of a thouſand traind. Of thoſe that are traind, all are not brought into the field. Of thoſe that are brought to the field in actions of greateſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, a number, it may be halfe neuer come to ſtrike ſtroke. Of ſo many millions in the Kings Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, not many thouſands may come to beare the ſhocke and burthen of the day.</p>
            <p>But by our vowes and prayers, all the whole Kingdome may fight at once. So many perſons, ſo many traind, armed men, ſo many ſoules, ſo many ſouldiers.</p>
            <p>Then if we cannot equall our aduerſaries in number and ſtrength of ſouldiers, if we can but get the ods by our prayers, what an aduantage ſhall we haue? when for twenty aduiſing, we ſhall haue ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:4335:8"/> times twenty thouſands praying to proſper their counſels, when for one thouſand fighting, we ſhall haue many thouſands of deuout ſoules like ſo many ſeuerall armies, or troupes, at leaſt in ſeuerall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, beſeeching, beſeeching ſaid I? I ſaid lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle. Beſieging God, <hi>Manu facta,</hi> with their praiers, and offering violence, for why not to God, as to the Kingdome of God, till he yeeld to goe forth with our armies, and to giue vs ſtrength, and victory in the day of battell.</p>
            <p>This was it that made King <hi>Dauid</hi> when hee ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med moſt weake to be moſt ſtrong. This was it that made him confident againſt their greateſt aſſaults. And if we, all we, that are neither for the head part, nor for the hand part, that are neither call'd to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult, nor fit to fight, would but ſeriouſly conſider, how by warring againſt our own corruptions, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions againſt God, how by approaching his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with our <hi>Petij,</hi> we might make him our friend, we ſhould to our comfort find, that there is no wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, nor yet vnderſtanding, nor counſell againſt the Lord, <hi>Pr.</hi> 21.30.</p>
            <p>Nor can I direct you a better courſe, then King <hi>David</hi> was in, who when his enemies were moſt furious, with moſt feruency importun'd God, that being freed from his troubles, he might haue liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to dwell in the houſe of the Lord all the dayes of his life: for thereby he was ſure to make his peace (you will confeſſe) with God, and then I ſay with men. For when a mans wayes pleaſe the Lord, hee will make his enemies to be at peace with him, <hi>Pr.</hi> 16.7. and ſo hath he by this meanes peace, both with God and men.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:4335:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> the King then appeares with his <hi>Petij,</hi> he had reaſon for it, he found comfort in it, and hence is it that he is not aſhamed to confeſſe it. Many vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the rod pray, and forget. <hi>Dauid</hi> did it, and to encourage and draw on others tels of it. Indeed it becomes Kings well to be Suiters to God. And then doe they aduance their crownes higheſt, when they caſt them loweſt at Gods feet. In old <hi>Rome</hi> the way to Honors Temple, was through the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Vertue, and the morall was good, but it's too generall for chriſtians, the way to honour now is by humilitie, a vertue not knowne amongſt the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, the firſt that admitted her was Religion, and ſhe alone keepes her; this <hi>Dauid</hi> knew, and thereby reſolued, that how high ſoeuer ſeated, he muſt not be high minded, but muſt by the gate of humilitie paſſe to heauen.</p>
            <p>The King then you ſee is a beggar, nor wants he his tongue, for he doth <hi>petere, Vnum petij.</hi> And though a zealous affection, be a continuall prayer, <hi>Qua ſemper petitur, quod ſemper optatur,</hi> whereby we alwaies aske that wee alwaies wiſh and deſire to haue. Yet the better to ſtirre vp his deuotion, and to impound his ſtraying fancies from gadding a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and that the reflection of his words might beat vpon his ſoule, he doth not onely <hi>Optare</hi> with his heart, but he doth <hi>Petere</hi> alſo with his tongue, a point <hi>Aquinas</hi> obſerued, <hi>Omnis oratio debet eſſe vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calis,</hi> euery compleat prayer ought to be vocall. For God the Creator of both, requires the ſeruice of the body as well as the ſoule. He is not ſo far out of loue with Ceremonies as ſome men take him to be, for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:4335:9"/> all their quarrell at putting religion in a ceremony. The tongue and the hand, and the knee, and the eye, and the habit, and the hat, and the outward ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, will ſometimes remooue a curſe, and bring a bleſſing when they want the heart, as is plaine in the ſtory of <hi>Ahab,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.</p>
            <p>In a word, neuer man neglected the dutie of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that did not firſt neglect the ceremonies of that dutie. From this root they grow vp to the higheſt pitch of impietie. Therefore this man, this King of ceremonies, <hi>Dauid,</hi> that went not to bed to pray there, but when hee was in bed roſe vp to performe that dutie; giues this reaſon of Atheiſme, and all impietie, and prophaneſſe euen the want of this <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tij, Non inuocauerunt deum, Pſal.</hi> 53.4. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it followes in this Pſalme, the ſeuenth verſe, <hi>Hearken vnto my voyce,</hi> (hee ſtill continues the vſe of his tongue) <hi>when I cry:</hi> he deſires not to be heard vpon other condition.</p>
            <p>Now as the greateſt muſt bee ſuiters, and the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteſt petitioners to God. So in our petitions, as hee likes not a proud peremptory faith, (I am not like o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, you know the Dialect) for <hi>Abraham</hi> muſt be but duſt and aſhes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. ſo he diſlikes as much diſtruſtfull humility, <hi>Qui timide rogat docet negare.</hi> And this the Prophet knowing, though he be a ſuiter; yet hee comes with confidence, hee will haue no nay. One thing haue I deſired, which I will require; with <hi>Iacob,</hi> though he be leſſe then all Gods mercies, <hi>Gen.</hi> 32. yet he reſolues not to let him goe before hee bleſſe him: Haue he would that hee deſired, though with <hi>Sampſon</hi> he tooke it out of the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:4335:9"/> Lions mouth. That he deſires, he will require.</p>
            <p>And ſurely this his importunity was a good ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of his familiary with God, for men vſe to be importunate with their friends, and ſuch as they may make moſt bold with.</p>
            <p>And therefore <hi>Abraham,</hi> who onely by name is called Gods friend, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20. and <hi>Moſes</hi> with whom God talked as with a friend, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33. are obſerued to haue beene moſt importunate with him of all other, the one for the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> pleading, and by degrees drawing him from fifty to ten, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. the other for the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> ſo preſſing God, that he was faine to entreat <hi>Moſes</hi> to let him alone, as <hi>Moſes</hi> was to entreat God to forgiue them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.</p>
            <p>And doubtles this was it that made <hi>Dauid</hi> ſo bold, to require and importune that hee had deſired, hee was a friend of Gods too, for what can bee required more of a friend, then to bee a man after his owne heart, and ſuch a friend was <hi>Dauid:</hi> hence it is, that he is not only a friend, but a friend to Gods friends, and an enemy to Gods enemies, for ſo it is in the verſe before my Text. When the wicked, euen my e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: See you a wicked man: he is <hi>Dauids</hi> enemy, becauſe Gods enemy. See you an enemy to <hi>Dauid,</hi> why then, ſure hee is a wicked man, implying that for which he conteſteth with God himſelfe. <hi>Pſalme</hi> 13.9. <hi>Doe I not hate them that hate thee.</hi> And then he proteſteth, that for which he conteſted; <hi>yea, I hate them with a perfect hatred, as though they were my enemies.</hi> So that there being ſuch a reciprocall aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, vpon intercourſe, betwixt God and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, that they are not onely friends, but they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:4335:10"/> maintaine a league offenſiue and defenſiue; ſo as they are friends to friends, and enemies to enemies; wee need not maruell he ſhould be ſo bold, as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that he had deſired. From <hi>Dauids</hi> affection we may learne to know our ſelues, If Gods friends be our friends, we may take comfort to thinke, that God is our friend too. If Gods friends bee our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, or Gods enemies be our friends, it is to bee doubted our league is likewiſe broken which wee had with God: That's for his affection.</p>
            <p>From <hi>Dauids</hi> confidence and importunitie, and Gods liking and allowance of it, great men may learne not to ſcorne to be importun'd by their infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors. The diſtance is greater betwixt God and man then can be betwixt one man &amp; another, and yet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> thought it no inciuility to importune God him ſelfe. <hi>One thing haue I deſired, which I will require.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It's a rule at Court, not to mooue a man againe in a ſuit, whom we haue lately troubled, I thinke be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there's little true friendſhip there, but he is the welcomeſt that commeth oftneſt to God. And hee that hath beene at him with his <hi>Petij,</hi> may bee the moſt bold with his <hi>Requiram.</hi> Such is the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of fauourites, both with God and men. His firſt bleſſings are cauſes of ſecond, and his by-paſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoures inducements to him, and ſo many encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements to vs, to call for more. Thus the Prophet pleades, <hi>Thou haſt beene my ſuccour, leaue me not,</hi> the ninth verſe of this Pſalme. A ſtrange motiue it were among men, Sir I haue lately troubled you, but I haue another ſuit, No, would hee anſwere, I haue already done well, trouble me no more. But
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:4335:10"/> he is the beſt entertained that comes oftneſt to God. He is not new fangled. <hi>Ego Iehova &amp; non mutor,</hi> he growes not weary of his friends. Once his and his euer, to teach vs, when once we put our hands to the Plough, to ſerue him euer, and to be ſure to make our <hi>Petij</hi> good with our <hi>Requiram.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe though importunity be often waited on with impatience, it's not ſo in <hi>Dauid,</hi> impatient hee was not, though importunate; ſo ſhould it be with vs. For <hi>Quae nondu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> data ſunt ſtulte negata putas?</hi> Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings are not denied when not preſently giuen, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times God is not fit, his time to ſhew his greater glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, is not yet come. Sometimes we are not fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue. Our Prophet knew that with God there was plenteous redemption. And therefore he that ſaid with himſelfe <hi>Requiram,</hi> ſaid to himſelfe <hi>Expectans expectaui,</hi> the beginning of the laſt verſe of this Pſalme, and though he tarry long, yet <hi>Suſtine Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum,</hi> the end of the ſame verſe.</p>
            <p>So, impatient he was not, yet importunate, <hi>That I will require.</hi> And no wonder if he were impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate, ſeeing it was but <hi>vnum,</hi> one thing that hee ask't, and <hi>vnum quiddam,</hi> ſuch a one. And this <hi>vnum,</hi> as it's ſet before, ſo it paſſeth through my Text, and euery part of it. He deſires one thing, to be in one place, to behold one beauty, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hauing fix't his deſires, well he would not change, but to this <hi>vnum</hi> would allot all the dayes of his life.</p>
            <p>He that makes a ſute but once to a friend, though it be ſomewhat diſtaſtfull, will look to ſpeed. <hi>Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> ſuſpected himſelfe, when he prayed to be heard
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:4335:11"/> at this time only. It implyed thus much. It's a great matter Lord, I now deſire to be reuenged for theſe ſcornes, and the loſſe of mine eies, with the loſſe of my owne life, and ſo many thouſands of mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. But ſtrengthen me at this time onely, and I ſhall neuer on earth make other requeſt, and then God heard him, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dauid</hi> comes oftner then once, but it's but for one thing, and that <hi>vnum quiddam,</hi> ſuch a thing as of all other was moſt pleaſing to God, he could haue deuiſed nothing for which hee ſhould haue beene more welcome, and yet hee is glad to importune God before he ſpeed. When the Breaſt is full, the Mother would bee drawne, but ſhe will endure a little paine to heare her childe entreate, or make moane for it. Doubtleſſe it's paine and griefe to God to with-hold his mercies, which he neuer doth but in mercy. If he delay to ſatisfie his children, euen that delay is another mercy. For if <hi>Dauid</hi> had ſped at firſt, it had beene <hi>vnum,</hi> but not <hi>primum,</hi> or if <hi>primum,</hi> not <hi>vnicum;</hi> it had beene one amongſt the reſt, not aboue the reſt, whereas the want made it his <hi>vnicum,</hi> moſt deare vnto him, <hi>Finiuit omnes cupiditates, remanfit vna illa quam petijt;</hi> he had quench't all other deſires, ſo as to delight in them, this onely remained as the ioy of his heart, and the longing of his ſoule.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>Vis impetrare, aliud noli petere, vni ſuffice, quia vnus tibi ſufficiet:</hi> Set thy heart onely vpon him that's onely able to fill thy heart. Vſe other things thou mayeſt: but lay thy reſt vpon this, to ſerue God.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:4335:11"/>
            <p>To thoſe that depend for comfort vpon any thing but this <hi>vnum,</hi> we may ſay with the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.21. <hi>You haue kindled a fire, and are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed about with ſparkes, and may not tarry leſt you burne.</hi> But this <hi>vnum</hi> will vpon the point cure all exorbitancies, and coole all diſtempers. For either it is that, or leades to that, wherein all generations haue beene, and ſhall be bleſſed. <hi>Abels,</hi> and <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Iohns</hi> Lambe, were all one Lambe. The wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans ſeed, and <hi>Abrahams,</hi> and <hi>Dauids,</hi> and the Virgins were all one ſeed. <hi>Dauids</hi> ſtone that the builders refuſed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 118. <hi>Daniels</hi> ſtone cut with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hands, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. <hi>Peters</hi> ſtone elect and pretious, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.6. are all one ſtone. <hi>Iacobs</hi> Shilo, <hi>Iſaies</hi> childe, the Euangeliſts <hi>Ieſus,</hi> are all one Ieſus, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out whom we ſee not Gods beautie. And as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41. both <hi>Pharaohs</hi> dreames are one. So may we ſay of <hi>Dauids vnum</hi> here, and Chriſts <hi>v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> in <hi>Luke</hi> 10.42. al's one, and the ſame <hi>vnum. Mary</hi> ſate hearing, and that was Chriſts <hi>vnum. Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> would be hearing, for the ſoule ſees by the eare, and ſo would he behold the beauty of the Lord, and that's <hi>Dauids vnum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This I gather, a man is eſteemed happy that hath that he loues, <hi>Vere autem foelix eſt, non ſi habet, quod amat, ſed ſi amat quod amandum eſt:</hi> For ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are more miſerable by enioying their deſires, then if they wanted them. It being moſt true, that it's ill to loue, worſe to loue and enioy that which is ill. And therefore God in mercy denies vs that wee loue, when we loue that which is not good for vs; and in iuſtice <hi>Dat amanti quod malè amat.</hi> So God
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:4335:12"/> heard the Iſraelites for fleſh: but not <hi>Paul</hi> for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moouing <hi>ſtimulum carnis,</hi> but <hi>illis dedit ad damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem, huic negauit ad ſanitatem,</hi> as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, in a temporall bleſſing he heard the Iſraelites to their damnation; in a ſpirituall bleſſing he denied S. <hi>Paul</hi> to his ſaluation.</p>
            <p>Then let euery man be carefull what he ſets vp to himſelfe for his <hi>vnum.</hi> If it be ſuch a thing as may be ſpared, let him not ouer-carefully or gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily deſire it. If it be ſuch as is approued, as grace or ſome meanes of grace, let him not for the want of it be deiected. Let it ſtill be his <hi>vnum,</hi> let him not ſpare to aske it, I ſay not three times, but thirty times three times, and either he ſhall ſpeed of that he askes, or he ſhall ſpeed of that ſhall be aequiua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent to it, either the temptation ſhall be remoued, or ſufficient grace to ouercome it.</p>
            <p>Then let Courtiers flatter, to get fauour; popular men diſſemble to gaine opinion; the ambitious la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to ſoare aloft, and when they are vp, to keepe themſelues on wing; the laſciuious drinke of ſtollen waters, as being the ſweeteſt, whatſoeuer they coſt them, though body, and ſoule, and all; yea, let all men ſet themſelues to their ſeuerall delights. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> you ſee deſires but one thing, and that one thing without exception, that <hi>he may behold the beauty of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe Gods beauty is not euery where to be found or ſeene. <hi>Dauid</hi> takes a ſure courſe, and deſires to dwell where God dwels. God dwels in <hi>Zion, Pſal.</hi> 9. And if he may dwell there, he ſhall ſurely ſee him and his beauty too; for <hi>out of Zion
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:4335:12"/> God ſhineth, Pſal.</hi> 50.2. And this was it that made his loue ſo great to the Temple, euen becauſe his honour dwelt there, that appeares not onely him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in beauty, but makes euery place beautifull where he is, for in the Verſe before named, <hi>Out of Zion,</hi> which is the perfection of beauty, God hath ſhined. So that whether you looke vpon the Lord, or the houſe of the Lord, there's nothing but beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in his eie.</p>
            <p>Hence is it that what he thought, he cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale. But tells vs ſometimes how amiable it is in it ſelfe. Sometimes how pleaſing to him. Euen ſo pleaſing, as he had rather be a doore-keeper in Gods houſe, then enioy any other honour. Here indeed was his heart. Gods houſe was his <hi>vnum,</hi> wherein he found all other comforts.</p>
            <p>Yea, if any affection be more violent in a man then other, here he findes matter for it. How haue men beene tranſported with that which they call beauty. And this, <hi>Dauid</hi> as you heard found in the Temple; yea, many times the fancies of men make thoſe appeare beautifull that are not: and as the Philoſopher obſerued, that <hi>Honor non eſt in hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rato, ſed in honorante.</hi> So may we truely, that beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty many times is not in <hi>amata,</hi> but in <hi>amante,</hi> for it's his affection makes her ſeeme ſo. But <hi>Dauid</hi> iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifies his affection to be well plac't, for the Miſtres of his thoughts the Temple is the perfection of beauty.</p>
            <p>No more maruell then if the Prophet were in loue, for indeed ſo he was; and as at another time he profeſſed, <hi>My heart is fixed, my heart is fixed.</hi> So
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:4335:13"/> might he now ſay, <hi>My heart is ſtricken, my heart is ſtricken, and I am ſicke of loue;</hi> whereof if any ſhall doubt, looke vpon him as he diſcouers himſelfe in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84. where you ſhall finde him in the exalta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of loues iealouſie. And of whome ſurely hee ſeemes to me to enuy the liberty and eſtate of Birds, in reſpect of that he was in when he could not come at the Temple. <hi>The Sparrow and the Swallow had built their neſts, euen by thine Altars,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dauid, but his ſoule longed and fainted for the Courts of the Lord.</hi> He that before had been the ſubiect of mens ſongs. <hi>Saul hath ſlaine his thouſand, but Dauid his ten thouſand,</hi> and had all the honour and content which a kingdome, and the grace and ſpeciall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of God could caſt vpon him, is now brought ſo low in his owne eſtimation, that the poore birds cannot build their neſts, but he muſt emulate their felicity, as if vpon that condition hee could haue beene a bird, ſo he might haue bred about the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. So that when he can he frequents it, when he cannot hee deſires it, and as a boone, the granting whereof had bin the ſumme of all bliſſe, he requires but this one thing, and while he obtains it, he looks and holds vp his hands towards it, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 28. And as the woman by touching Chriſt got vertue out of him; ſo doth he, as after the Prophet <hi>Daniel, Dan.</hi> 6. by ſetting his face to that quarter where the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſtood, fetch force of affection and zeale in his prayers to God, and in a holy dotage (I ſpeake it with reuerence) ouer the Temple, as ouer ſome chaſt Virgin, whom he had choſen for his Spowſe, he lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth, and fainteth for her, and that ſo impotently,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:4335:13"/> as if all that were neare her, though vnreaſonable creatures, exceeded him in the truth of all reall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect contentment.</p>
            <p>Might he then haue the liberty that Sparrowes and Swallowes haue, how would he vſe it; ſurely euen as the Birds doe. The Sparrowes-houſe ſhould be his, and hee would build him a neaſt with the Swallow. For he would not call in, but dwell there.</p>
            <p>God ſaith, my habitation is in <hi>Zion,</hi> and <hi>Dauid</hi> prayes that his habitation may be there too. So that vnleſſe God depart from his Sanctuary, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 8. <hi>Dauid</hi> will dwell in it. It was ſaid of the Centuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Chriſtus non intravit tectum ſed cor.</hi> So may we ſay of <hi>Dauid, Chriſtus intrauit cor Davidis,</hi> and that made him ſo deſirous, <hi>Habitare in tecto Dei.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Foxes to their holes, Lions to their dennes, Birds to their neſts, Fiſhes to the Sea, Beaſts to the fields, Children to their mothers, Schollars to their ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, Tradſmen to their ſhops, Merchants to their ſhips, Wantons to their chambers, Rich men to their cheſts, where their treaſures, and their heartes are, all men to their delights. <hi>Dauid</hi> would bee at the Temple. This is the obiect of his thoughts, the Theater of his delight, the ioy of his heart, the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter about which all his deſires were turned, for he would not dwell there, but as if it were the body and the ſoule, hee would neuer part, for there hee would be all the dayes of his life.</p>
            <p>He had ſought it with importunity, and if hee may ſpeed, he and the Temple will neuer be ſeuer'd. He that ſo importunately deſir'd it, had experience, how pleaſing a thing it would bee to enioy it, how grieuous to want it.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:4335:14"/>
            <p>Carnall men cannot reliſh ſpirituall content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, they are fooliſhneſſe vnto them, till they be throughly acquainted with them. For this is the difference betwixt heauenly &amp; earthly pleaſures: In earthly pleaſures, you ſhall euer find it true, that <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcit adeptum, quod accendit deſideratum,</hi> Thoſe things we hotly purſue before wee get them, ſped once, we contemne, and <hi>Qui ſatietati occurrit, ſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etatem incurrit,</hi> we are ſatiated with that which we tooke as a medicine againſt ſatietie. But it's not ſo with ſpirituall pleaſures. Before we haue them wee neglect them. Get them once and we loue them a-life: ſo that temporall pleaſures are ſlightly regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded after, ſpirituall before we enioy them. Before we enioy temporall pleaſures wee are madded, not after; after we haue taſted ſpirituall pleaſures, wee more purſue them, not before. This of the Prophet was a ſpirituall contentment: and a contentment it muſt needs be to behold beauty, and a ſpirituall contentment to behold the beauty of the Lord; therefore would he keepe it all the dayes of his life.</p>
            <p>And well was this added to behold the beauty of the Lord, for there are many that dwell there, and yet neuer behold his beauty whilſt they are there. As forward they ſeeme as <hi>Dauid</hi> to come to the Temple; but that's the end of their <hi>Petij,</hi> they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be ſeene there, they care not to ſee God when they are ſeene there: for many come for many re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, and for the moſt part they finde that they come for. He that comes not to ſee the beauty of the Lord, ſhall neuer be cheer'd with the ſight of it.</p>
            <p>Some come to gaze, ſome to walke, ſome to meet
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:4335:14"/> their acquaintance, ſome for faſhions ſake, ſome for feare of law, the goſpell cannot draw them, ſome to ſpy a fault, ſome to pick a quarrell, and ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps for worſe: I haue heard trauellers ſay, that in <hi>Italy</hi> many looſe matches are made there. But <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> farre otherwiſe comes to behold the beauty of of the Lord. And this is the laſt part, but the firſt ſpheare, by vertue whereof all the reſt moue, and as the Iewes ſpoil'd themſelues of their garments, to entertaine Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 21. ſo doth King <hi>Dauid</hi> here ſpoyle himſelfe of all the deſires of his heart, of all the contentments of his life, for this one boone, that he may behold the beauty of the Lord.</p>
            <p>Some tranſlate it <hi>Voluntatem</hi> ſo the old tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and it may beare it well enough, but then it muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the good will of God, the beames of which beauty we may behold by that light in the firſt to the Epheſians at the fift verſe, <hi>Who hath predeſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vs to be the adopted through Ieſus Chriſt, vnto himſelfe, according to the good pleaſure of his will,</hi> and well might this be his meaning, for it followes in the ninth verſe of this Pſalme, <hi>O God of my ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> for therein is the good pleaſure of his will ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted vnto vs, to this are we adopted, to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinated, that we may be ſaued: in which forme whoſoeuer beholds God, will not long for another beauty.</p>
            <p>Others tranſlate it, <hi>Voluptatem, delectationem, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moenitatem, pulchritudinem,</hi> all things much ſet by, and yet to be ſet by as of no eſtimation, not once to be lookt vpon in reſpect of that which <hi>Dauid</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, for he that made the eye ſhall not he ſee, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:4335:15"/>he that made beauty, ſhall not he be beautifull?</p>
            <p>I, but <hi>ſmoake goes out at his noſtrils, and a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming fire out of his mouth,</hi> Pſ. 18.8. <hi>The Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines tremble for him, and the Hils melt, and the earth is burnt vp at his ſight,</hi> Nah. 1. how then ſaw <hi>Dauid</hi> beauty in his face? True, But as wee read in the ninty Pſalme, as a man feareth, ſaith <hi>Dauid,</hi> ſo is Gods diſpleaſure: ſo may I ſay as a man beleeues &amp; loueth, ſo is Gods good pleaſure, <hi>Voluntas Domini;</hi> hence our Sauiour, <hi>according to your faith be it vnto you,</hi> Matth. 9.29. and according to your loue ſo is Gods beauty, for iuſt as we ſtand affected to God, doe we behold God reflecting vpon vs, <hi>Ille placet Deo cui Deus placet,</hi> he pleaſeth God that's pleaſ'd with God. This beauty and this pleaſure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light which the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tooke in God, was it that made him eſteeme all things dung in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of him, ſo was he taken with this beauty. This was it that made our Prophet breake out in the 42. Pſalme <hi>As the Hart brayeth after the riuers of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> (when he is purſued by the hunters, and is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to fall downe, as a prey before the dogs, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of his thirſt) <hi>ſo my ſoule panteth for thee O Lord, to appeare in thy preſence;</hi> yea this beauty was it that moou'd him to make that challenge and proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Whom haue I in heauen but thee, and I deſire nothing in the earth with thee,</hi> Pſ. 73. Not onely no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing aboue him, but nothing with him. His fleſh may faile, &amp; ſo may his heart, yet ſo long as he may looke vpon this beauty, <hi>Thou art</hi> ſaith he to God, <hi>the ſtrengh of my heart, and my portion for euer,</hi> the 26. verſe.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:4335:15"/>
            <p>Yea from the ſight of this beauty was it, that the Apoſtles fleſh did in a ſort faile, that it did not faile, for he deſired to be diſſolued, and to be with Chriſt: and the Church in the <hi>Cant.</hi> was ſo farre rapt in this contemplation of this admirable heauenly beauty, which ſhe ſaw in our bleſſed Sauiour, that impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent of delay, and as ſhe after profeſſeth ſick of loue <hi>Cant.</hi> 2. ſhe requeſts in the firſt of <hi>Cant. Let him kiſſe me with the kiſſes of his mouth.</hi> And now ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine, Aliud deſidera, ſi maius, ſi melius, ſi ſuavius inveneris,</hi> if hauing felt ſuch pleaſure ſuch delight, if hauing ſeene ſuch comelineſſe, ſuch beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, as the good pleaſure of the Lord, manifeſted vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee in the forme of a Sauiour, and bringing ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation vnto thy ſoule, doth repreſent vnto thee, goe to and loue ſomething elſe, if any thing be greater, be better, be ſweeter.</p>
            <p>Yet all this while we doe not ſee him face to face, but once we ſhall, and know him as wee are knowne. In the meane time this is our comfort, that as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, though we cannot ſo ſee him, though there be not here <hi>Poteſtas videndi,</hi> yet here there is <hi>Gratia promerendi ut videre poſsimus,</hi> and though we ſee him not here in glory, yet here wee ſee him in grace, and no man beholds him face to face in the next world, that by grace beholds not his beauty in this: therefore our Prophet deſires of God in the ninth verſe of this Pſalme, that ſince he would ſo gladly behold his beauty, it would pleaſe God not to hide his face from him.</p>
            <p>Onely let me exhort you, that while you ſeeke this beauty, and make it your <hi>Primum,</hi> you neglect
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:4335:16"/> not, deceiuing your ſelues (as a way to it) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooue the beauty of the Church and Common wealth, which principally conſiſts in order, and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie. For theſe two make decency, which is beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; for that which is beautifull is decent, and that which is decent is beautifull, and neither of theſe can be without order and vnitie. Hence the Apoſtle as if all beauty were in order, <hi>Let all things be done decently and in order,</hi> 1 Cor. 14. and laſt.</p>
            <p>And indeed order and vnity, which is nothing but explicite order, are the outward beauty, the beauty of the body of the Church, the inward beauty, or the ſoules is holineſſe, that's it makes her all glorious within. But that beauty wee cannot ſo well diſcerne, as beleeue,: it's onely ſeene of God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the reſidence of it is in the heart, and vnleſſe we in ſome meaſure pertake of that beauty, and bee gracious by it in the eyes of God, by being holy as he is holy, he will neuer ſhew vs his owne beauty, for they muſt be beautifull themſelues in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, that enioy ſuch a beauty as his is: therefore the ſpouſe in the <hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6. would be ſet as a ſeale on Chriſts heart, that if it were poſſible, the print might not more reſemble the ſeale, then ſhee her Sauiour.</p>
            <p>And indeed this is the prime feature, that takes him, this is that beauty that wounds his heart. <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.9. when we thus looke vpon our Sauiour, wee o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome him, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.4. for this aboue all things makes his deſire towards vs, <hi>Cant.</hi> 7.10. and there's no ſurer poſſeſſion we can haue, no greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt we can make, then by poſſeſſing and ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:4335:16"/> by the deſire of thoſe wee conquer and poſſeſſe.</p>
            <p>Feare keepes good quarter, but it's onely by the rod; remoue that, and we recoile, but deſire yeelds all, and alwaies. If his deſire be to vs, we doe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come him, and all his by that conqueſt, all his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, all his pleaſures, all his graces, all his ioyes are enfeofed and eſtated vpon vs.</p>
            <p>Then get holineſſe, <hi>the beautie of holineſſe,</hi> 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 16.29. for that's it is ſo attractiue, ſo ſtrong, ſo preualent.</p>
            <p>But whileſt you labour for this inward beautie, you muſt take care likewiſe for the outward: For though holineſſe make her glorious within; yet if we neglect vnity and order, her cloathing will not not be as is fit for the Kings daughter, and for his Spouſe that is the chiefeſt of ten thouſand, of wrought gold and Needle-worke. She may be beautifull, and yet want her ornaments wherewith ſhe ſhould be dreſſed. And I doubt not, but when our Sauiour in the fourth of the <hi>Canticles,</hi> brake out into that admiration of her, <hi>Behold thou art faire my loue, behold thou art faire, thine eyes are like the Doues;</hi> and ſo paſſeth to her haires, and her teeth, and her lips, and her necke, and her breaſts; hee tooke pleaſure euen in theſe outward ornaments, of Order and Vnity, which are nothing elſe but vnanimity and vniformity. And in expreſſe tearmes we haue order, which is vniformity, when he compares her teeth to a flocke of ſheepe in good order, the ſecond verſe of that Chapter, there's vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity. And when a multitude of men like haires
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:4335:17"/> on a Virgins head, are well ſet, the firſt verſe, and are all like one entire body, there's vnanimity. When the Churches lips are like a thread of Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let, there's vniformity. And when her talk is comly, both in the third verſe, there's vnanimity; for where it's croſſing, there's no vnity.</p>
            <p>This is her necke built for defence. Let the holy Church of God be beautified, and guarded with vnanimity, and vniformity; and they will be to her as a thouſand Shields, and as all the Targets of the ſtrong men, <hi>Cantic.</hi> 4.4.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſſe, that of late whatſoeuer our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward beauty hath beene, we haue wanted the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, both in Church and ſtate. And ſurely I ſee no great cauſe to hope for amends in the Church, at leaſt in theſe parts; where, with many, nothing but ſingularity is accounted ſanctity; whileſt men hold of this man, and of that man, of this Church, and of that Church, and yet by no reaſon, by no authority can be brought to ſee that they are car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall; though the Apoſtle concludes againſt them ſtrongly as conuinced, when one ſaith I am <hi>Pauls,</hi> and another, I am <hi>Apolloes,</hi> 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 3. are ye not carnall?</p>
            <p>And for the State, we cannot but acknowledge the diuiſions in it, whileſt by the practiſes of ſome louers of themſelues; the Prince hath beene rent from the people, and the people from the Prince, as hath appeared by thoſe diſtractions in the higheſt Court, the onely meanes to ingratiate Prince and people, one to another. When the bed entertaines iarres betweene man and wife, what ſhall reconcile
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:4335:17"/> them? when the mercies of men are cruell, what can ſoften them? and when the houſe of Vnity and Order, the Fountaine from whence it ſhould flow, and ſtreame out to the whole Land, is in iealouſie and combuſtion, what can the fruit or effect be but confuſion? And thus it hath beene, but bleſſed be God, that of late hath giuen vs cauſe to hope for better things, and that God that put it into his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties heart to call a Parliament, ſo bleſſe it, and continue peace and vnity in it, as with one heart, and one hand they may ioyne againſt the enemies of Religion, and the State, to the glory of God, the honour of his ſacred Maieſtie, and the ſafety of his Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>What if hitherto the cloudes, and ſtormes of contention haue intercepted thoſe rayes of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, which otherwiſe might haue cheared vs, and made vs ſtrong againſt all forreine aſſaults &amp; feares, and haue enabled vs to haue ſupported the weake hands of our confederates and allies, that haue fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnder the burthen of the common enemy. Yet let vs not be diſcouraged.</p>
            <p>It's Gods method many times in matters of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to proceed by contraries. Thus he began. So was <hi>Eue</hi> curſed before ſhe had the promiſe of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing. Thus he went on. So was <hi>Sarahs</hi> wombe dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp, before he made it fruitfull, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18. Yea, thus hee continued. So hee made <hi>Ioſeph</hi> a bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaue, before he brought him to honour. And hee muſt himſelfe in a Basket (a leaking Boat God knowes) be caſt into a Riuer, <hi>Ex.</hi> 2. that muſt carry Gods people thorow the red Sea. Could any thing
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:4335:18"/> be more croſſe, then to thinke that that childe, that in a baſket was ready to ſinke, ſhould carry ſo great a people through a Sea, and yet dry-ſhood. You ſee in my Text, <hi>Dauid</hi> longs, and faints, and prayes, and importunes, and ſets his reſt vpon it, as his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bliſſe, before he can be admitted to dwell in Gods houſe, to behold his beauty. And this is our hope, and I am perſuaded my truſt is not in vaine, that God in this courſe hath beene pleaſed to make ſtrife and diſtraction, the ground and foundation of that beauty of vniformity and vnanimity, which ſhall henceforth commend and grace this Church and State. Thus did our bleſſed Sauiour, out of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidelity of <hi>Thomas</hi> worke faith: thus did God cauſe <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> to ſpring out of the barren wombe of <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſurely then ſhall we begin to haue aſſurance, that God hath not forgotten to be gracious; when out of the former ſeeds of faction and diuiſion, hee ſhall cauſe the beautifull fruits of loue and vnitie o grow. O how good and comely a thing is it for brethren to dwell together, in vnitie; this is it makes vs beautifull, and comely, and commends vs to Gods affection.</p>
            <p>Therefore if Saint <hi>Paul</hi> will vouchſafe to entreat thoſe he may command, this ſhall be it, <hi>That they ſpeake all one thing, that there be no diſſention, that they be knit together in one minde, and in one iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.10. And if Saint <hi>Peter</hi> will haue one thing remembred aboue all the reſt, hee will bring it in, as a parting blow, whereof they muſt take ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall knowledge, <hi>Friends bee yee all of one minde</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:4335:18"/>1 Pet. 3.8. and in the ſecond to the Philippians after he had conteſted with them, and coniured them, by whatſoeuer was deare vnto them, <hi>If any conſolation in Chriſt, if any comfort of loue, if any fellowſhip of the ſpirit, if any compaſsion and mercy,</hi> what of all this? <hi>fulfill my ioy.</hi> This was the vtmoſt of his am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, the period of his deſires; wherein would he haue his ioy fulfilled? what would doe it? <hi>That yee be like minded, hauing the ſame loue, being of one ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and of one iudgement.</hi> And what was the end of this his ſerious importunity? that nothing be done through contention, or vaine glory, which are like the breaking in of waters, that cannot be ſtaied.</p>
            <p>If God haue beene long angry with his people, and once begin to be reconcil'd, why then, <hi>They ſhall be my people, and I will be their God, and I will giue them one heart, and one way,</hi> Ier. 32. yea this was our Sauiours prayer laſt before his paſſion, as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> records it, <hi>that they may bee all one,</hi> Ioh. 17.</p>
            <p>Euen ſo Lord Ieſus, let vs be all one, in our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections and deuotions, <hi>that with one mouth we may praiſe God,</hi> Rom. 15. all one in iudgement, that wee may proceed by one rule, both in things pertaining to Religion, and gouernment Eccleſiaſticall, and by one rule, in ciuill matters, and things pertaining to the common good and the maieſtie and honour of the King and State. That this whole Kingdome being as a Citie that is at vnitie in it ſelfe, nay, as one family, nay if it were poſſible, as one heart, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in reaſon ſeaſon'd with religion, gouernes, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, like a iuſt and a potent King, and the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:4335:19"/> yeeld obedience, like ſo many humble faithfull, dutifull ſubiects, the whole Nation, may be a Nation after Gods owne heart, and with confidence ſay with the Spouſe in the <hi>Cant. My well-beloued is mine and I am his.</hi> So ſhall we enioy Gods beauty, and he take pleaſure in ours. So may the temporall fruit, by the mariage of King and people, in a hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py bond of loue and vnitie, be anew brood of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, for men and women being married begat men and women like themſelues. But Prince and people happily ioyn'd, if they beget, it muſt be king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes like themſelues by a new propagation and enlargement.</p>
            <p>So ſhall the ſpirituall fruit be ſuch, by this beaute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous coniunction, that ſo many of vs as are thus ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſhalbe his children, and adopted for heires, &amp; e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery heire a King to reigne with our bleſſed Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, in the Kingdome of his Father; which the Lord grant, for the ſame his deare Sonnes ſake, to whom with the holy Ghoſt bee all glory and praiſe for euer and euer.</p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4335:19"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
